It's no secret that our society has a digital device problem. Ninety-two percent of Americans own a smartphone. Research has found that we are more connected than ever before and yet feel more isolated, more lonely, more depressed than ever before.
How's that possible? Social scientists call this a collective action problem. We all agree that these devices are having a detrimental impact on our mental health, and yet it feels virtually impossible to withdraw from these devices because they are so interconnected in our lives. So what can we do?
Good morning, church. Welcome to our final week of our digital detox series. This is obviously a bit different than a lot of our typical sermon series, but I hope you found it well worth the time. I wanted to invest some significant time in this really important issue because I think it's something that if we don't pay attention to, it will happen to us rather than us making decisions about it.
And so hopefully you found it valuable and challenging, and hopefully you're doing some things around your screen time. And like Jamie said earlier, next week we're going to be kicking off a highly anticipated series on the book of Revelation, kind of getting back into our normal preaching through books of the Bible.
So, if you deleted your news apps for the digital detox, I'm going to want you to re-download those, because we're going to be talking a lot about the news and when the tribulation is going to be happening.
And that was a joke. It was a really bad joke, and if you didn't get the joke, do not worry. Church culture stuff, if you didn't get it, it's okay.
And yeah, the book of Revelation has often been kind of misused and misinterpreted, and what we're going to look at over the next many weeks is that it was actually a book written to seven churches who were suffering persecution for being followers of Jesus, and the book was intended to encourage them to persevere.
And so even this morning as we prayed about the kind of rejoicing and weeping that's happening in the room, I have been just, my heart and mind has been changed by Revelation chapter 4 and 5, which gives us an image of what the throne room of God looks like right now, so that those of us who are suffering have a picture for what's ultimately real.
And what we see on the throne is a lamb as though it had been slain. And this is such an encouragement to those of us who are suffering because it tells us that the victory that we have, the hope that we have for the future, is rooted in a person who suffered the same sufferings that we did.
It's actually the way in which sin and death and the powers and principalities were conquered, not with overwhelming force, but with sacrificial love. And it was God's eternal and good plan that He Himself would suffer alongside of us.
And so even this Father's Day, I'm thinking about those of you that have lost your father. I'm thinking about Jesus as the suffering servant. And as far as we can tell in the Scriptures, He Himself lost His father.
And the book of Revelation continually points us to Jesus as the Lamb who was slain, the one who endured the same sufferings that you and I endured, and yet came out the other side with resurrection power.
And that is our hope that we are clinging to, no matter what we're going through, that we have a suffering servant who sits on the throne.
So looking forward to that series, I hope you will join us and ignore my bad joke-making skills this morning, all right? Let's pray.
Father in heaven, we are just again grateful that we get to enter your throne room in worship, not just with the people in this room, but with the people across the country and across the world.
From every different denominational background and every different theological stream and tribe.
God, those of us who have bowed the knee to Jesus, enter your throne room alongside the angels and multitudes of heavenly hosts, declaring that you are holy, holy, holy.
God, that is not a just trite thing we do a few times a year to encourage us and to make us feel better.
It is the eternal story. And it's so easy to lose sight of that story on this side of the apocalyptic curtain.
It's so hard to see the victory of the slain lamb in a world that's so broken and fallen. And so God, give us eyes to see and hope for a future. It's in Jesus' name I pray. Amen.
All right, well, today I have a big goal of putting a bow on the entire Digital Detox series with the hope of giving all of us really one big practical application.
Not just one practical application point for today's message, but for all four weeks of the Digital Detox series. And to do that, I want to review where we've been throughout this series.
It's summertime, so some of you have missed some of the weeks, and that's okay. But I want to make sure we're kind of tracking along with where we've been.
And I'm afraid, as I was writing my message, I'm afraid it might feel a bit disjointed until we get to the end. But I'm optimistic that I can land the plane without too much turbulence.
If you stick with me. And that is a challenge. Because I know you guys respond well to challenges. So stick with me, and hopefully by the end, I think the plane will land with most of its parts intact, okay?
Week one, we talked about how our screens are one of the primary instruments of formation as humans. The screens consume our time and therefore are making us into a certain type of person.
We realize it or not. They become so intertwined into our everyday lives that we don't even realize how much they're forming us, or how often they're forming us.
And Michelle talked about Romans 12:1 and 2, that we are to be transformed by the renewing of our mind, not to be conformed into the image of this world, but transformed.
And the screens play a really important role in that. And then week two, we said our screens are often pumping our minds and our hearts with voices of people and
things that are competing with Jesus for the allegiance of our lives. We are getting voices and encouragement to follow after things that are less than the thing we were made to follow after.
And that is the voice of the Good Shepherd, who leads us to abundant life. And then last week, we talked about that. Of all of those voices, there's one primary influencing voice behind all of them.
And that's the voice of the serpent in the garden, who comes to Adam and Eve and who comes to each one of us through our screens and our devices and promises us a
shortcut to abundant life. By seizing the definition of good and evil from God for ourselves, rather than trusting and obeying the God who created us, we are invited to trust and put our hope in our definition of good and evil to experience life.
And today, we intentionally wanted to end this series on Father's Day with an invitation to all of us, but especially to those of us who have spiritual leadership and influence in the lives of children.
I want us to really think intentionally about what we want our relationship and our kids' relationship with screens to be moving forward.
And as adults in the room, this decision should be made with intentionality. It shouldn't just be something that happens to us. Our screen habits should not be something that we just participate in, but we make active decisions about.
And so I think the most practical invitation I can give to each of us at the end of this series is to invite us to craft what I would call a rule of life around our screens or our devices, both for us as individuals and for our families, for the children that are under our care.
And rule of life is a term that is in vogue in many Christian circles nowadays. We've talked about it a little bit in the Practicing the Way series, but it is not a new idea.
It traces back through the monastic movement to the desert fathers and mothers to the early church who developed it out of their Jewish influence, steeped in the Old Testament story.
This is not a new idea. And what a rule of life is, at its most basic point, it is just a set of intentional practices, rhythms, and relationships designed to help people abide in Christ and to be formed into His image.
And so what my hope is, is that we will just take a look at our lives and our practices and that we would create a set of regular practices and rhythms and restrictions for ourselves in order to abide in Christ and to be formed into His image.
It's just really practical. I want to be careful that we avoid any type of legalism or like the word rule just comes with, if you grew up in a church where there were lots of rules, it comes with some baggage.
What I'm not telling you to do is to write down all of these rules and follow them strictly and perfectly forever, and if not, you're a terrible person.
What I'm saying is that we have a relationship with a good shepherd who wants us to hear and listen to his voice, and so what if we just created some rhythms and practices in our life that allowed his voice to be the primary voice we focus on?
There's a ton of freedom in this. There's a ton of, "Oh, no, my rule of life says I'm not supposed to watch TV today, but it's storming outside."
Okay, I will receive an invitation from the Father to watch TV when it's storming outside, right? Like, it's just like freedom, and it's an invitational thing.
And I would even argue that when we looked at the Garden of Eden last week, that we were looking at an invitation from God for Adam and Eve to live into their own rule of life.
He gave them all of the good trees in the garden, and he invited them to walk with him in the cool of the evening and to enjoy all of his good creation.
And yet, he invited them to set one self-imposed boundary, right? He didn't stand in front of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil and keep them from eating it.
He invited them to place a boundary for themselves around that tree that would lead them into the image of the Father, that would allow God himself to define good and evil for them.
And yet, they refused to allow that invitation to be there. They stepped across that boundary, and they chose to take from the tree.
And that decision began forming them not into the image of the Creator, but into the image of creation.
And they worshiped creation rather than the Creator. The original humans rejected God's rule of life for their own and did what was right in their own eyes.
And the reality is, whether we acknowledge it or not, we all have a rule of life.
We all have a rule of life both in our embodied life and with our devices.
We have maybe not intentional practices, rhythms, and relationships, but we have practices, rhythms, and relationships that are forming us.
We have habits with our screen times and our devices that are forming us, and the question becomes, what are they forming us into?
And if they're not forming us into being more like Christ, then we should really, those of us who have bowed the knee to Jesus,
we should really think about that intentionally, both for us and for our families.
So, with the rest of our time this morning, I want to look at one of the foundational passages in the Old Testament where I see God inviting His people into this type of thing, this rule of life.
It's not called a rule of life in Deuteronomy, okay? We're just, we're putting a category on something that exists in Scripture.
I just want you to, we're good there? Okay, we're good. God invites His people into this,
into this set of intentional practices, rhythms, and relationships designed to help them become the people that He's inviting them to become.
And at the end, I want to consider what happens when those people allow themselves to drift from these practices slowly over time.
Not on purpose, maybe. Not with ill intent, but just slowly drifting away from God's practices. What happens?
So, Deuteronomy chapter 6 is where we're going to be. I usually give you a heads up,
so you can get there before I start reading. I did not do that. I apologize. I'm stalling right now so that you can get there.
Genesis, Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers, Deuteronomy. It's at the beginning. All right.
Deuteronomy 6, starting in verse 1, it says, "Now this is the commandment,
the statues and the rules that the Lord your God commanded me to teach you,
that you may do them in the land to which you are going over to possess it, that you may fear the Lord your God,
you and your son and your sons' sons, by keeping all the statutes and the commandments which I command to you,
all the days of your life, and that your days may be long.
Hear, therefore, O Israel, and be careful to do them, that it may go well with you,
and that you may multiply greatly as the Lord, the God of your fathers,
has promised you in a land flowing with milk and honey.
Hear, O Israel, the Lord our God, the Lord is one.
You shall love the Lord your God with all of your heart and with all of your soul and with all of your might.
And these words that I command to you today shall be on your heart.
You shall teach them diligently to your children and shall talk about them when you sit in your house,
when you walk by the way, when you lie down, and when you rise.
You shall bind them as signs on your hand, and they shall be as frontlets between your eyes.
You shall write them on the doorposts of your houses and of your gates.
And when the Lord your God brings you into the land that he swore to your fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob to give to you,
with great and good cities that you did not build, and houses full of good things that you did not fill,
and cisterns that you did not dig, and vineyards and olive trees that you did not plant.
And when you eat and are full, then take care lest you forget the Lord,
who brought you out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of slavery.
"It is the Lord your God you shall fear, him you shall serve. By his name you shall swear you shall not go after other gods,
the gods of the peoples around you, for the Lord your God is a jealous God, lest the anger of the Lord your God be kindled against you,
and he destroys you from the face of the earth."
So the book of Deuteronomy, we have kind of the final compilation of God's law
to his people. It's right before they enter the Promised Land. It's the final reminder of what the story of God is to the people of God
before they enter the Promised Land. It's one of the clearest, Deuteronomy 6 here is one of the clearest and most well-known places in
Scripture where we see God's agenda for the world. The story of God is that God is inviting a people into relationship
who would submit to his definition of wisdom, his definition of good and evil,
and who are committed to cultivating Eden-like conditions to the world around them. This is what God wants to do
through Israel. He is inviting them into a covenant relationship. They have said, "Yes, we want to trust your definition of good
and evil. We want you to lead us and guide us and direct us, and we want to cultivate your Eden-like circumstances
to the world around us." And Deuteronomy 6 is Moses' central speech given to the people as the summary of this story of what
God wants for them to do as they enter the promised land. And ultimately, what he gives for them in this passage is a
reminder, rhythms, and the risk of forgetting. You guys see what I did there? Three Rs? Come on. Come on. Thank you. Thank
you. Sometimes the Baptist still comes out in me. So let's look first at the
the reminder. The first three verses, Moses starts the speech by reminding the people who they are.
The Lord your God commanded me to teach you these things. The Lord your God is inviting you and your
sons and your sons' sons to enter into a covenant relationship with him that will ultimately lead to your abundant
life where things are flowing with milk and honey. And so the first thing Moses wants his people,
God's people, to understand as they're about to enter the promised land is he wants them to remember
that ultimately this whole thing is based on their relationship with God. They don't obey God's rules
or laws out of religious duty to earn God's favor, to receive blessing. They do so because they are the
covenant people of God. It is their identity, and it is an invitational identity. God didn't force them
to be his people. He invited them to be his people, and they surrendered to his covenant. And so God is saying,
"You are my people. Therefore, you let me define good and evil, and you let me define what wisdom looks like,
and I will produce Eden-like circumstances in your community, and I will spread Eden-like circumstances
through your community to the world around you." And if you read the Old Testament law, there's so many
beautiful passages about taking care of the widow and the orphan and the foreigner. It's not just
about Israel. It's about Israel becoming what God wanted all people to become by surrendering
to his definition of good and evil and taking care of the world around them. And so he's reminding his
people, who they are, and then he reminds them of the rhythms of their life that are built, that they've
built their identity in. And in 6:1, we get three Hebrew words that kind of encompass a lot of different
things. It says, "Now this is the commandment." Notice that singular. And the next two words are
plural. This is the commandment, the statutes, and the rules. And there's three kind of categories
that Moses is referring to here, and different scholars have different opinions on it. But
I think the easiest way to summarize it is first and foremost, there's a reason why the
word commandment is plural. And then the next thing that Moses says out of his mouth is, "Hear, O Israel,
the Lord our God, the Lord is one. You shall love the Lord your God with all of your heart, soul,
mind, and strength." This is the central commandment to the covenant people of God. This is the one
thing. It's no wonder when the Pharisees ask Jesus what is the most important
commandment. He quotes this, "You shall love the Lord your God with all of your heart,
soul, mind, and strength." And he goes on to say, "And you shall love your neighbor as
yourself." The second commandment is like it. This is the central commandment for the
people of God. You can get lost in the 613 commandments that you find in the Old
Testament, but this is the commandment. It is a relational commandment. It is an
invitation to submit to God out of love and surrender. This is the point of God's
covenant people. Love the Lord your God with all of your heart, soul, mind, and
strength. Love your neighbor as yourself. Central, singular commandment. Around it
are rules and statutes. The rules are kind of the moral law of the Old
Testament, all of the do's and don'ts and the Ten Commandments. The statutes are
more like the ceremonial law, the cultural practices and rhythms that set them
apart, like Passover and Day of Atonement and all of these kind of cultural
things. And Moses is saying all three of these things are built in to us as a
people, but it's all with the center point of loving God and loving our
neighbor. The central invitation to God's covenant people is to love God. And
outside of that are these moral boundaries and cultural practices, and all of those
things are aimed at helping people love God and love neighbor. They function like
a fence around a playground that sits near a busy highway.
None of us as parents would take our kids to a playground that sits on the edge of a
slope that runs into a busy highway with no fence. But as Americans, we love freedom
and we hate boundaries, right? We hate fences, unless, never mind, I'm not going to do that. Sorry.
Different sermon, different day. Americans, we hate fences. We hate, we love freedom.
We love freedom. We were built on this. Our identity, our culture disciples us into the idea of freedom.
But the Scriptures regularly give us the idea that it's actually some healthy boundaries inside
of the system that actually allow us to be the most free. We can enjoy the playground
much more when there's safety around the edges. This is the Garden of Eden.
This is, hey, there's all of these trees. There's all of this goodness and creation. Enjoy it all with freedom and surrender
to me, just not this one thing. Put a fence around something that keeps us from experiencing God's goodness.
And we are not Israel, but we are God's covenant people in the new covenant. And the central command for us is to love God and our neighbor.
And around that are moral laws that you will read about in the New Testament. And there are cultural rhythms
all aimed at helping us grow in love of God and love of neighbor. This is not a legalistic system.
All of these practices are built around this one central commandment. And they're all aimed at helping us grow into love of God and love of neighbor,
which leads us to the rhythms. And I don't know about you, but when I think about the moral law and the cultural practices,
especially in the Old Testament, I tend to think about them in a very formal and rigid way, right?
You read through the Torah and you've got all of these like strict rules of when to show up to the temple,
of how to show up to the temple, of what you bring to the temple. There's these very strict and formal ideas around the cultural practices and moral law.
But if you read what Moses says here, he tends to, it's not that those things aren't true, but he goes a step further.
And in this passage, he talks about cultural practices that are much more ordinary.
"You shall teach them diligently to your children. You shall talk about them when you sit in your house, when you walk by the way, when you lie down, when you rise, you shall bind them as a sign on your hand."
These are very daily, ordinary rhythms of life. And the reason he does this is because Moses, like most pastors,
we know that a handful of communal religious and cultural practices will not be everything that God needs, God's people need to remember God's story and submit to his authority in their lives.
Like me, the priests only had spiritual influence over the people when they gathered to the temple, which in the grand scheme of things is a very small percentage of their lives.
A majority of their lives was lived in the ordinary daily rhythms of working and playing and laughing and just surviving.
And it's in those ordinary regular rhythms where they're not gathered together corporately as the people of God at the tabernacle or the temple.
It's in those daily rhythms when they are most prone to lose sight of God's story and to be dragged away into the story of the culture around them.
And so Moses seems to extend the cultural practices to the ordinary moments of life in the household and community.
He says, "Diligently and daily teach your children about God's love."
Keep His commandments on your heart. Talk about them when you relax at your house, when you travel to soccer practice, before you go to bed, and when you wake up.
Moses is inviting the people of God to create a functional rule of life that shapes their ordinary and everyday habits.
This, again, is my primary application point for our entire series, is that if we do not have regular practices and rhythms in our ordinary daily lives,
then what will we do when we sit down to relax, when we travel, when we sit down to eat, before we go to bed, when we wake up?
What will be written on the walls of our houses?
It's no coincidence to me that all of these times that are listed in Deuteronomy 6 are all times that oftentimes we just pick up our phones.
These are times and places that most of us are staring at screens, filling our lives with the voices of thieves and robbers competing for our attention and our allegiance to Jesus.
And this isn't primarily an individual rhythm, but a corporate one. He says, "Teach them to your children."
He doesn't say, "What do you do with your time?" He says, "What does the community do with your time?"
And parents, if we do not place boundaries around our children's devices, our ordinary lives will be consumed by them.
And it is not an easy task. Your children will fight you. And they will say, "But, my friends."
But none of us would let our kids go to a playground beside a busy highway without a fence.
And so why are we comfortable doing the same thing while they sit in our living rooms on couches with endless content at their fingertips?
And again, this isn't just a job for parents, but for grandparents and uncles and family friends.
Raising children takes a village, and the nuclear family did not exist in the Old Testament.
And so if we want to become a people, communally, who grow in love of God and love of neighbor,
we all have to be intentional to rehearse the story of God and His goodness to the community around us.
It won't just happen when we're under this roof. It has to happen as we go throughout our ordinary, everyday lives.
And if we are not intentional, we will naturally drift towards a different story.
The question isn't, will we have rhythms? The question is, will those rhythms be intentionally designed around God's story or accidentally designed around someone else's?
Which leads me to the third R of the day. We're cruising. The risk of forgetting.
Moses ends kind of this part of his speech after giving them a reminder. You've got to talk about it everywhere you go.
You've got to rehearse the story of God. He ends with a risk of what will happen if they don't do that.
He says, "The Lord is going to bring you to the land that he promised your forefathers with great cities.
Life is going to be good and comfortable and abundant, but take care lest you forget the Lord who brought you out of the land of Egypt,
out of the house of slavery. Take care, pay attention to the story that you are living into,
because if you are not intentional to remind yourself of the story of God's goodness to bring you into
abundant and eternal life, then you will live into a different story."
He says, "People often begin to enjoy the gifts of God apart from the presence of God,
and we slowly worship creation rather than the Creator. Our lives will be formed by a different story.
It won't happen immediately or drastically. It does not happen overnight,
but slowly over time, God's people will forget their story.
We will find ourselves back at the tree of the knowledge of good and evil
with that same choice that Adam and Eve had,
and that same doubt in our mind that God is good because we haven't rehearsed the story.
We haven't reminded ourselves of all that God has done for us.
We haven't set our minds on things above, and we will find ourselves again
or our children will find themselves again at the tree of the knowledge of good and evil
with the same decision to make.
Will I trust that God is good, and will I trust that his definition of wisdom is good,
and it will lead me to abundant life, or will I seize that definition for myself?
And if we have not rehearsed the story, if we have not reminded ourselves of God's goodness in our lives,
the temptation is slowly over time, our lives will be built on a different story.
We will reject God's wisdom for our own.
We will choose what seems right in our own eyes.
And unfortunately, this is exactly what happens to our original audience.
They move into the promised land, they settle down into a new normal,
and towards the end of their settling down into the new normal,
Moses is kind of the next leader in line after Moses, Joshua,
who's leading the people, who's reminding the people of the same thing that Moses is doing in Deuteronomy 6.
He confronts the people with the same decision, and he makes a bold declaration
that many of us are very familiar with, thanks to Hobby Lobby.
You know where I'm going? Choose this day whom you will serve.
Thank you, Hobby Lobby. But as for me and my house, we will serve the Lord.
This is Joshua's bold declaration. One generation removed from Moses,
reminding the people of the same thing. We're entering the promised land.
We know what might happen. We might be tempted to forget, but me, Joshua, I, as your leader,
I am choosing today that me and my household will serve the Lord.
And all of the nation of Israel agrees with Joshua.
Yes, we will serve the Lord. And then we read in Judges 2:7,
"And the people served the Lord all the days of Joshua,
and all the days of the elders who outlived Joshua,
who had seen all the great work that the Lord had done for Israel.
And Joshua, the son of Nun, the servant of the Lord, died at the age of 110 years."
Lord, take me before that. Sorry.
"Joshua died at the age of 110 years,
and they buried him within the boundaries of his inheritance
in the hill country of Ephraim, north of the mountains of Geash,
and all the generations who were gathered to their fathers.
And there arose another generation after them
who did not know the Lord
or the work that he had done for Israel."
Joshua and the people of God, they make a bold declaration of surrendered obedience,
but evidently, somewhere along the way, they lost sight of the regular rhythms
of their families and their communities.
They stopped rehearsing the story of God,
and the consequence is that their children,
the children of those who had just entered the promised land,
on the power and might of God's visible victory,
they didn't know the Lord or the things that he had done,
which leads them right back to the tree of the knowledge of good and evil,
and the defining attribute of this generation in the book of Judges
summarizes this generation with this statement,
"Everyone did what was right in their own eyes."
So we've got a generation of people making a bold declaration that us, me, my household,
we're going to serve the Lord in the next generation,
and their children are back at the tree of the knowledge of good and evil
with the same decision to make.
Will we trust the Lord and his definition of goodness,
or will we seize it for ourselves?
And they don't know God or what he has done for them.
And my fear is that if we are not intentional in this generation,
mothers and fathers and grandmothers and aunts and uncles,
if we are not intentional, not just to show up to church on Sunday every once in a while,
not to just get plugged into a small group,
but if we are not intentional to daily rehearse the story of God in our communities and in our families,
our children might just forget the goodness of God.
They might not even know him to begin with.
They might just know that their parents know him.
So what are we doing, church, with our ordinary daily rhythms?
Are they saturated with us rehearsing?
And I'm not talking about like strict, like you got to have morning Bible study.
And I'm talking about like just as you're reading Deuteronomy 6, as you go along the way, as you travel, as things come up, as your kids ask you questions about creation, about every normal, ordinary thing, are you reminding them of how good God has been and of his invitation to surrender to his definition of good and evil?
And are we modeling that type of surrender, or are we just telling our kids that God is good and you should surrender to him while we don't do that?
Do we have intentional rhythms aimed at reminding us of God's wisdom and helping us to cultivate Eden-like circumstances?
Or do we have unintentional rhythms captured by screens that are causing us to fall back into the trap of defining good and evil for ourselves?
So my final challenge, my one application point, landing the plane with hopefully not too much turbulence, is to consider your daily and weekly rhythms.
Consider your screen time and how it impacts and influences those rhythms. Dads and moms and grandparents and aunts and uncles and close friends, how are your screen times impacting your relationship with the next generation?
What are we teaching them about life and abundance and goodness in the way that we interact with our screens?
And what rhythms and boundaries are we placing in their lives around their screens so that they have space to hear from God, so they have space to remember God's goodness in their life?
And what might a rule of life, again, not a legalistic hard and fast rule, but what might some practices and rhythms look like for you and for your family around screen times?
I put a book recommendation in the bulletin, and we'll put it in the newsletter this Sunday. It's called "Habits of the Household."
It's a phenomenal book for parents about this very topic. It's very practical. It's written by a dad with a full-time job who doesn't act like it's easy, which is always good, right?
It's always good to have somebody say like, "Hey, this is what we do, and this is how it fails and how hard it is."
It's a wonderful book, but specifically chapter four is on their habits and rhythms around screen time.
I would recommend it highly to any of you who are wanting to look into this. Again, not legalistic rules, but rhythms that flow out of a relationship, all reinforced around the central commandment.
There's rules and statutes. There's plural stuff all around, but it's all around the central commandment to love the Lord our God with all of our heart, soul, mind, and strength.
And so as we kind of land the plane on this message, land the plane on this series, I wanted to share a video testimony with you of a person in our congregation who's kind of taking this idea of developing a rule of life for her screens and for her kind of daily rhythms and routines.
So I'd love for you to check this out, and then I'll come back up and we'll end.
The moment I caught myself mindlessly scrolling through Venmo is when I realized I might have a problem.
Hey, my name's Carmen Lawyer, and my husband William and I have been coming to Canvas since August, so almost a year.
The digital fast was something that really spoke to me, and I sent Ryan an email, and he was like, "Oh, can you talk about your story?"
So, here I am. I used to have a 30-minute commute to work, and you can only listen to so much music, and so I started listening to podcasts.
And through that time, I learned this concept of parenting your phone, being present. I was like, "Intriguing idea," but I didn't really feel convicted, necessarily.
January, Passion 2020, and I finally realized, "Okay, I might have a problem." So, I gave my friend my phone, and she set a one-hour social media limit for me.
The next day, my hour of social media time was gone by noon, and that was me trying to pace myself so I didn't run out of time.
After that is when I opened Venmo, and without even intentionally doing it, and found myself scrolling.
And that slightly terrified me a little bit, the fact that I was doing something that I didn't even realize I was doing.
But I still didn't care enough. My heart wasn't behind it. I wasn't surrendered to the Lord.
So fast forward to 2024, 2025, and I was teaching my students. I was trying to teach them for a 50-minute science class, and all of my kids had phones.
One in particular comes to mind. She told my team of teachers and I regularly that she would go home, take a nap, wake up, eat dinner, and then stay up all night on her phone on social media.
No wonder I was having a problem trying to engage her in my class. I continued this journey of trying to parent my phone, and in January 2025, I decided to delete all social media from my phone.
I was trying to get serious about this. I saw what was happening with my kids, and I was like, "I don't want to be like that."
In that time, I read like 13 books in the month of January, one of which was "The Anxious Generation." While I was reading that, I learned that average users receive a notification about every five minutes.
Heavy users, much like myself or my students, more than likely, receive a notification about every minute.
The next day at work, I put my phone in my desk drawer, and over several days, I started taking less and less work home.
I was more focused during my planning periods and getting my work done at work. It was amazing.
I wanted to find this balance of not being completely anti-technology, but also not letting it consume every bit of me.
I found this app called BePresent, and my social media use dropped to less than 25 minutes per day.
Ironically, I found the app on social media. But what was the terrifying thing was I didn't need a passcode or someone holding me accountable,
because they used the same methodology to keep you off of your phone that the big tech companies used to keep you on it.
I kind of carried around with that journey, but I still didn't love how much I was still being on my phone.
So I deleted all my social media from my phone this past January, and I decided to not put it back on my phone.
I felt so much freedom in that, and so I decided to have all my social media only on a Wi-Fi iPad.
I now believe I have a lot more healthy boundaries with technology.
Because Meta emails me on a regular basis about all I'm missing out on, and I'm like, "Okay."
Instead, I do things like read books now. I love doing puzzles. I learn piano. I'm learning piano. I'm learning guitar.
I have more presence in my everyday life.
The most poignant example, I guess, that I can think of right now is I took my first solo trip to South Carolina back in March,
and I stopped at a Chick-fil-A, and it was the first time that I was somewhere without someone else,
and I didn't have the ability to scroll on my phone or my iPad,
and I was sitting around and looking at the people around me and just enjoying being where I was.
I was being very present in the moment, and ironically, I saw a lot of people on their phones,
but I'm pretty sure I also saw someone on their first date, and I was like, "That's actually kind of cool."
What God's taught me the most in this is it's really not about social media,
but rather it's been about my attention and my heart all along.
I was giving so much attention to my screen, and all that my attention wasn't going to God, my family, and all the people around me.
I didn't just get my time back. I got my space back. I got space to pray, space to hear His voice, space to worship Him.
Space to be present. And I'm not, like, anti-technology. I still, obviously, I have an iPad.
But I've learned that anything competing for my attention can slowly take the place that God's meant to have, whether I realize it or not.
This journey has been less about deleting the apps and more about learning how to steward my attention in a way that honors Him.
And it's still very much a journey. I don't want to make this sound like I've mastered this, because I most definitely have not.
Even after deleting social media from my phone, I still catch myself, to this day, searching for Facebook and my apps out of habit.
It's not, again, it's not about perfection and arriving at this perfect moment, but it's being aware of where my attention is going
and continually surrendering that and stewarding it well to what matters the most.
Thank you for listening to this part of my story, and I hope you feel encouraged in some sort of way.
Well, I hope that you were as encouraged by Carmen Story as I was. I love preaching.
I love standing up here and encouraging with God's word, but there's not many better things than hearing stories from people
who are putting God's word into practice. And one of my favorite themes from her story was her emphasis on how
space away from screens allowed her to hear the voice of God. And that's really what this series is all about.
That's what my heart has been throughout this series, is that we would just create enough space in our minds and our hearts
so we could really hear the voice of God and what He's inviting us into, because the voice of God is always going to lead us to a more abundant life
than the one we experience when we are not listening to it.
So that theme of listening to the voice of God, it leads me into an important announcement that I need to make today.
We had to make it today, so sorry about the awkward timing. But we made this announcement to our volunteers on Wednesday,
and we wanted to share with the rest of you today that over the past few weeks, Pastor Michelle has been hearing from God about an
opportunity to become the school counselor at Jordan Springs Elementary School in her neighborhood. This has been one of those
hearing from God things that was challenging for her to hear, because she loves your kids and our kids so much.
She loves our church so much. But she has discerned that the Lord is leading her to step down from her full-time role
as children's pastor and calling her to a new ministry at the school. She is not leaving the church.
She still plans on being involved in our kids' ministry, but obviously her level of involvement will change significantly
as she steps into this new role. And those of us who have walked with Michelle over the past few weeks
around this decision are very sad that her role is changing. We love her. We are so thankful for her.
But we are also extremely excited for her and for the gospel impact that this will have on one of our local
public schools. This is kingdom stuff. Our vision is to cultivate the kingdom of God in Winchester
as it is in heaven, and that doesn't primarily happen under this roof. But it happens as each one of us
take the good news of Jesus to where we live, work, and play. So not only are we excited for Michelle,
but we are also expectant for us as a church because God brought us Michelle at the right time. She actually discerned her
call to step into children's ministry in a service like this one, when a need for a children's
director was announced on a Sunday morning about eight years ago at Canvas. So please, be in prayer for
Michelle and for this new incredible ministry opportunity that she has. Be in prayer for our
church and our leadership as we seek the Lord to figure out what this means for us moving forward. And I
hope that this testimony of hearing from God's voice, both from Carmen and from
Pastor Michelle, will encourage all of us and remind us of the importance of
listening for God's voice in our everyday life. What might God be inviting you into?
Maybe it's not a big career change. Maybe it's an unconfessed sin you need to
address, forgiveness that you need to extend, a neighbor that you need to reach out to. I
don't know what it is for you, but I know that God is often inviting us to partner with him in
his work around the world. And if we don't listen, we might miss out on so many blessings
that God wants to pour out through us and on us as we step into obedience to him.
So I'm going to pray to end our gathering, and then I think what we need, a little bit different
this morning, I think we need our kids, our parents to pick their kids up through this hallway
because there's ice cream chaos happening out here. And it's just going to be a
chaotic morning, and I'm sorry about that, but that's just the nature of buying an old fire hall
and putting a church in it is there's lots of hallways and not a lot of big gathering spaces.
So we're going to pick up our kids out here. There's an ice cream fundraiser in the lobby.
We kind of opened up the office parking lot out on the front side of the building if you want to get ice cream
and hang out and talk to people and fellowship. So please be doing that.
And yeah, let's pray. Father, we are just grateful for another week,
another opportunity to think about your voice in our lives, to think about our daily and regular rhythms.
And are they centered around you? And are they reminding us of your story of deliverance and healing and salvation?
Or are we living into a different story, a story of the culture around us that does not know you, and does not know the things that you have done?
God, are we allowing you to define good and evil? Or are we seizing that decision for ourselves? God, may this theme, just may you bring it to our minds and our hearts this week by your Holy Spirit.
Help us to create healthy rhythms and boundaries that allow us more space to hear from you. And God, we just trust that as your people step out into obedience to your invitations in their lives, that your kingdom will spread.
That Eden-like conditions will go beyond just what happens in our families and in our churches, but to the world around us. God, do this for your glory, for our good, and for the good of our neighbors. In Jesus' name I pray. Amen.
Church, peace.